Guide to the Daniel Collins Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Daniel Collins family papers
1775-1893
MS 894
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
Correspondence, receipts, music, log book pages (1811), and printed matter. The correspondence is largely among members of the family and also includes two letters to Daniel Collins' father, also named Daniel Collins. The music includes fifteen manuscript pages with words.
Collins, Daniel, 1776-[184-]
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The papers were separated from the David Chittenden Collins Papers (MS 886) in 1979.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of a few letters, bills, and other miscellaneous papers concerning Daniel Collins (1739-1810?) and his son Daniel (1776-1849?), a ships' block maker. Pertaining to the elder Collins are two letters, one from his nephew Joseph Tufts, Jr., describing the death of Tufts' mother several weeks after giving birth (1801), the other from Collins to his son reporting on the health of the family (1802). There is one letter from the younger Collins to his second wife, Sophia Walker, written shortly after their marriage in 1812 from Washington, D.C., where Collins was seeking work in the navy yard, and two letters addressed to Collins by a friend, Thomas B. D'Wolf of Nova Scotia, reporting on old friends (1836).
Other papers pertaining to the younger Collins are his certificate of citizenship, receipts, a page from his commonplace book, and an insurance policy. Other items in the collection include anonymous printed and manuscript poems and texts and settings for a number of hymns, several pages from a log book of 1811, and an assortment of receipts, printed matter, and a facsimile of the memorial to the Colonial Assembly of Connecticut from the Connecticut Militia of 1775.
These papers were separated from the David Chittenden Collins Papers (Manuscript Group Number 886) in 1979. The provenance of the Daniel Collins Family Papers is unknown.
Biographical / Historical
Daniel Collins was born in 1776. He was a ships' block maker. He was married to Fanny Walker on May 8, 1803. He may have died in 1849.
Death; Families; Music; Shipbuilding; Shipping; Collins, Daniel, 1739-1822; Collins, Daniel, 1776-[184-]; Tufts, Joseph, 1783-1835; Collins family
- Inventory
  - Daniel Collins (1739-1810?): correspondence, 1801, 1802 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Daniel Collins (1776-1849?)
    - Correspondence, 1812, 1836 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Certificate of citizenship, 1808 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Receipts, 1809, 1811 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Page from Daniel Collins' book, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Poems, 1793, 1852, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Music, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Log book pages, 1811 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Receipts, notes, printed material, 1828-1893, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Poems by Daniel Collins, 1793 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Facsimile of memorial to Colonial Assembly of Connecticut, 1775 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Insurance policy, 1826 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Printed matter, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)